<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Asindu's Journal</title><description>A public journal about thoughts going through Asindu's head.</description><link>https://asindu.xyz</link><language>en</language><copyright>Copyright 2024, Asindu Drileba</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><generator>Hugo - gohugo.io</generator><docs>http://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs><atom:link href="http://asindu.xyz/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><item><title>The Nature of Technology Book Review</title><link>https://asindu.xyz/posts/the-nature-of-technology-book-review/</link><description>&lt;p>Last year I read a book titled &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;The Nature of Technology&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong> by one W. Brian Arthur. After finishing it, it was one of those books that I wish everyone read. Especially if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in technology, technological progress, the notion wealth creation or economic growth. &lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brian Arthur is one of those &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;complexity theorists&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>, that is, people that study the relationship between groups &amp;amp; the individual components that make them up.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An example is a stock market, you cannot trade stocks by yourself, you need to be in a group to trade stocks with each other.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The stock market can be looked at as a lumpy, single or independent system even when it is made up of many agents and the properties of the lumpy stock market may be very different from the properties of an individual agent in the market. Complexity theorists call this a Complex System. &lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For people that are not aware of such a definition of complex systems, studying literature of these complexity theorists may just look like inter-disciplinary science.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brian Arthur in this book, brings about the mind set of thinking about technologies as a complex system (smaller components interacting to form larger groups) and uses it to provide some insights about technology that may be easy to understand but not blatantly obvious.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I say this book is a must read because it provides insights into some action points incase you want to achieve some things — somethings that I think everyone might say are good to achieve.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="so-why-should-you-read-the-nature-of-technology">So, why should you read &amp;ldquo;The Nature of Technology&amp;rdquo;? &lt;a href="#so-why-should-you-read-the-nature-of-technology" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>If you want a blueprint for generating tech start-up ideas or come up with inventions that people will find useful the book is for you.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>I often see discussions on social media, amongst friends, politicians on TV, on how cities, countries can become technologically competitive with other regions. One question for example is usually how can we have something like silicon valley in Africa, in Europe etc. Basically other communities wanting to replicate technological success equivalent to that in silicon valley (or just the West) in their own communities. If you want to know how this book is for you. (Hint: the answer isn&amp;rsquo;t more homework time for children).&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>A childhood friend of mine and me used to talk about inventors. A lot of people&amp;rsquo;s answers to this question is something like &amp;ldquo;things to invent are over&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;the low hanging fruit is gone&amp;rdquo;. This book describes why there is only more stuff to invent and why with every subsequent invention there is actually more potential for people to invent more items or technologies. That is, there will be more, lower hanging fruit as more technological progress is made and more things to invent. The book properly explains why.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The aim of this blog post is to write about some of the take aways I got from the book which may address some of the discussions I outlined above.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It would be inaccurate to call this a summary the book.
The book is short (just under 300 pages), but it&amp;rsquo;s very information dense. So dense I think it is not be possible to soak in everything on first reading.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="take-aways-from-the-book">Take aways from the book. &lt;a href="#take-aways-from-the-book" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Now, for the meat of the article below, are some of the 3 most important take aways I got from reading the book.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="1-technology-relies-on-phenomena">1. Technology relies on phenomena. &lt;a href="#1-technology-relies-on-phenomena" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The meaning of phenomena is something an event or pattern that can be observed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An example is the phenomena of electromagnetic waves that were investigated by the likes of Heinrich Hertz, Oliver Lodge and Guglielmo Marconi. Which are the basis of telecommunications TV Signals, Radio Signals, GPS, WiFi — basically all of wireless communication. &lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another example is nuclear power that is based on the understanding of phenomena happening inside atoms.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So what, this is obvious? you may ask. The important insight isn&amp;rsquo;t that technology relies on phenomena.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>It is the fact that the discovery of phenomena is a prerequisite to the creation of new technology.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let us first think of some practical implications of the above statement. If you want to have an ecosystem that creates new technology.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We have to invest in basic scientific research and by this I mean both &lt;strong>teleological&lt;/strong> &amp;amp; &lt;strong>non-teleological&lt;/strong> research whose purpose is to document, curate and study different phenomena. &lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Teleological research&lt;/strong> means investing in research whose use is obviously known. Like looking for the cure of cancer, if a break through in made in this field we know exactly how it will benefit society.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What however I think is more important and unfortunately suppressed or discouraged by most institutions is the investment in &lt;strong>non-teleological research&lt;/strong>.
That is, the investment into research who&amp;rsquo;s use is not clearly outlined.
An example is the study of flocks of birds, the origins of the universe, the behavior of prime numbers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So why should we invest appropriately in research that isn&amp;rsquo;t obviously useful? I gave you the answer earlier. &lt;strong>phenomena is a prerequisite to technology&lt;/strong>, you need to find the &lt;strong>phenomena first&lt;/strong> before you can find something useful to do with it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It will not be obvious what a particular newly discovered phenomena can be used for. When electricity was discovered for example by the ancient Greeks. It was not exactly obvious that it can be used to make power smartphones and light bulbs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The discovery of so called quantum phenomena for example made it possible to invent the laser &amp;amp; the computer transistor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also, special properties of some prime numbers for example are used in public key cryptography to secure communication across networks like the internet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We simply cannot invent the cryptography first, and then come up with the mathematical properties/phenomena of the numbers later.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So if we want people to find new phenomena that may potentially be used to build new technology we need to;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>a) Allow students, researchers to peruse topics that are not obviously useful.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>b) If you want to get ideas for new technology to invent. A good way to do so it is to simply study &amp;amp; curate phenomena, in physics, mathematics, biology, economics or psychology e.t.c. And then try to leverage it to do something useful. If you are successful and the first to do so, you probably would have invented new technology.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I will leave you with an excerpt from the book that expands on this point further.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;em>The process is not one that can be easily controlled from the top down. There is always a temptation for governments to pursue science with particular commercial aims in view. But this rarely works. Had there been a stated purpose to quantum physics in the 1920s, it would have been deemed a failure. And yet quantum physics has given us the transistor, the laser, the basis of nanotechnology, and much else besides. Building a capacity for advanced technology is not like planning production in a socialist economy, but more like growing a rock garden. Planting, watering, and weeding are more appropriate than five-year plans&lt;/em>&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="2-technology-is-combinatorial">2. Technology is combinatorial &lt;a href="#2-technology-is-combinatorial" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I was listening to the Lex Friedman interview with Jeff Bezos. And he mentioned something that is relevant to this section of the blog post. &lt;sup id="fnref:5">&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Jeff Bezos mentioned in the interview that he identifies with himself as an inventor, what is relevant to the discussion here however is that Jeff Bezos also said that to &amp;ldquo;invent&amp;rdquo; Amazon he used components that were already invented. That is, the logistics infrastructure that was used by Amazon to make deliveries and the online payments processing infrastructure.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>These two components were necessary for Jeff Bezos to invent Amazon but he didn&amp;rsquo;t have to invent them. He combined two already existing technologies, online payments processing infrastructure &amp;amp; logistics infrastructure for fulfilling deliveries. This is why I say that technology is &amp;ldquo;combinatorial&amp;rdquo; meaning that it is a combination of other technologies.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But Amazon isn&amp;rsquo;t only built up of two components i.e prerequisites that it needs to work. It is built up of programming languages, browser technology, networking infrastructure, microprocessors, electricity and many other components.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These many other technologies &amp;ldquo;combine&amp;rdquo; to make Amazon possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some people suggest that it is more difficult today to invent new technology because all the &amp;ldquo;low hanging fruit is gone&amp;rdquo; or because &amp;ldquo;we are running out of things to invent &amp;ldquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The good news is that if we think of technology as being combinatorial. Then it would mean that the number of new technologies to discover will only increase with time i.e with each new discovery.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Why? For illustration the fact that technologies are combination of other technologies means that there is no basket from which we are pulling discoveries from.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The people that suggest technological progress will slow down assume that there is a finite amount of things to be discovered, and that each new technological discovery brings the bucket is closer to being empty.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If we are to think of technologies as a combination of other technologies then we shall conclude the above suggestion may be false.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Consider two technologies &lt;code>'A'&lt;/code> and &lt;code>'B'&lt;/code>. If we create a new technology by combining those two we now have a new technology called &lt;code>'AB'&lt;/code>. So in total we have three technologies i.e &lt;code>'A'&lt;/code>, &lt;code>'B'&lt;/code> and &lt;code>'AB'&lt;/code> instead of two.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now we have three technologies to combine instead of two.
Which gives us &lt;code>'A'&lt;/code>, &lt;code>'B'&lt;/code>, &lt;code>'AB'&lt;/code>, &lt;code>'AAB'&lt;/code>, &lt;code>'BAB'&lt;/code>, and &lt;code>'ABAB'&lt;/code>. The new technologies &amp;lsquo;AAB&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;BAB&amp;rsquo;, and &amp;lsquo;ABAB&amp;rsquo; are a result of combining &lt;code>'A'&lt;/code>, &lt;code>'B'&lt;/code> and &lt;code>'AB'&lt;/code> together. Now we have six technologies to combine in different ways that will even lead to more technology that can also provide more ways for technology to create new technology. This is the phenomena referred to by Brian Arthur as increasing returns. &lt;sup id="fnref:6">&lt;a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>The mathematical abstraction above illustrated that starting with only two technological components, combining them in different ways gives us a larger set of technologies and thus a higher potential to create new technologies not less.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In reality we can apply this method of thought. Think of the combination of chemicals for example used make lithium ion batteries, these batteries can be used to make other technologies like Electric Cars, Laptops, Smart Watches and autonomous drones.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The framework can also be applied in software. Many software developers creating open source libraries for example does not make it less likely for developers to create new software.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The available open source libraries can be combined in many ways to create new open source software which will also make it possible to make new combinations of software libraries that will be used to create an even larger set of possible software.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So if technological progress actually slows down in the real world the reason should never be that &amp;ldquo;we are running out of ideas&amp;rdquo; or that, &amp;ldquo;the law hanging fruit is gone&amp;rdquo;. The reasons may be more cultural that technical. It is less likely to be less hours spent on home work or lower IQ points of the population.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also, if you are a wannabe inventor, another blueprint for creating ideas is to think of how to combine different technologies and &lt;strong>then later&lt;/strong> think of what this combination can be used for — Instead of first thinking about a solution/problem and then trying to look for the right combination that will solve the problem. &lt;strong>This can be regarded as a form of non-teleological invention. That is, inventing something whose purpose or use u may not know of at first creation.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="3-technology-transmutes">3. Technology transmutes &lt;a href="#3-technology-transmutes" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>My last take away from this book is that &amp;ldquo;Technology transmutes&amp;rdquo; and to transmute means &amp;ldquo;to change form&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brian Arthur defines technology as a set of techniques or devices used to satisfy a human need.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So to him things like postal services, Yellow Page telephone directories, accounting techniques, drafting of building designs and writing are all forms of technologies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following technologies listed above however don&amp;rsquo;t remain as they are. When new technological break troughs that are otherwise unrelated are made. They often encounter these existing technologies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This encounter then fosters a transmutation i.e the recent break troughs from otherwise unrelated fields interact with previous/old/existing technologies to create something that is related both but also different.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A clear example of this may be the postal service. Computer technology was initially developed for its number crunching abilities — very little todo with communication, but combined with networking and suitable user interfaces. It encountered the concept of a postal service and transmuted/transformed it into a new sub industry of electronic mail (e-mail services like Gmail).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We see this with the writing of books or documents on pen/pencil &amp;amp; paper being transmuted into the use of word processors like Scrivener or Microsoft Word. Writing in a computer&amp;rsquo;s word processor software is very different from writing on a piece of paper with a pen. Papers do not require keyboards, nor do pens require electricity. The two new paradigms of technology are not obviously related.
Computer technology &amp;amp; software encountered the act of writing and transmuted it from writing on paper with a pen to using a keyboard on computer software. Although the activity is still writing i.e the output of text, by a human using a set of devices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Yahoo Web Directory trying to mimic Yellow Pages business directory.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Accounting/book keeping transmuting into spreadsheet programs like Microsoft Excel or software like Quick Books.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The drafting of building designs on pencil &amp;amp; paper transmuting into something like ArchiCad.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Televisions programs transmuting into something like YouTube.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And Radio stations transmuting into something like Podcasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So what is a good action point for a wannabe inventor, venture capitalist, or school that wants to foster creation of new technology?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We need to develop consilience amongst professionals, students and researchers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Consilience is the exploration of several disciplines (especially those that are not directly related) and then using the insights from multiple disciplines to think in terms of analogies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An example of the role of consilience is in the development of ArchiCad. ArchiCad is a software program used by Architects for drafting building designs. So you might think that it was developed by Architects right? No.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Architects did not invent ArchiCad because they are too busy being top tier architects.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>ArchiCad was created by one, Gábor Bojár a Physicist by training and Jonathan Ingram, a Civil Engineer and computer science PhD.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Anyways here is the concern. &lt;strong>Architects are not updated enough in what&amp;rsquo;s happening in the field of computing/programming to know what programs can be built to be useful — and computer scientists/programmers don&amp;rsquo;t know much about Architecture for them to make programs that will be comprehensively useful to Architects&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This dilemma of requiring &amp;ldquo;off-topic&amp;rdquo; knowledge in order to create a new form of technology is something that is recurrent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You cannot design software for music producers, like FL Studio, Logic Pro or Cubase. If you have neither produced music nor worked around producers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You cannot come up with an MRI scanner for detecting cancer tumors like Raymond Damadian did&lt;sup id="fnref:7">&lt;a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. If you do not know about the basic composition of a cancer tumor. It will not matter how fantastic an electric engineer you are if you don&amp;rsquo;t have this &amp;ldquo;off-topic&amp;rdquo; knowledge in the realm of medicine that describes the basic properties of a tumor in a human body.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you want an extra blueprint, in your tool box of ways to come up with new technologies, it would be that you should look into what other people are doing in other professions, or activities that are not obviously relate to each other and this will give you a larger possible set of activities that you can &lt;strong>transmute&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I believe this action point of developing consilience, reveals some of the short comings of specialization and vindicates the value of hobbies/exploration/pondering outside our fields of scholarship, research and professions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An interview I recommend related to this topic is one given by David Eliot Shaw, I have linked a video to the exact time stamp where he proposes this &amp;ldquo;right brain thinking&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;thinking in analogies&amp;rdquo; as advice to young and upcoming scientists &lt;sup id="fnref:8">&lt;a href="#fn:8" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">8&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like I said this should &lt;strong>not&lt;/strong> be regarded as a summary of the book it is more of a review and a few take aways. If you like technology you are very likely to enjoy the book and I suggest you read it.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Nature-Technology-What-How-Evolves/dp/1416544062">Here is a link to the book&lt;/a>. The full title is, &amp;ldquo;The Nature of Technology: What It Is and How It Evolves&amp;rdquo; by W. Brian Arthur&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complex_system">Wikipedia page on complex systems&lt;/a> is really good. I suggest you have a look at it. You may want to look at the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_Farol_Bar_problem">El-farol bar problem&lt;/a> also devised by Brian Arthur if your interested in this complex systems view of the stock market.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>Great BBC documentary on electricity. &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gtp51eZkwoI&amp;amp;t=7010s">Linked is a time stamp to the section that covers electro magnetic waves&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4">
&lt;p>In the book Anti-fragile by Nassim Taleb, he writes extensively about this in a section titled &amp;ldquo;Non-teleological Tinkering&amp;rdquo;&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:5">
&lt;p>Link to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DcWqzZ3I2cY">Lex Fridman episode with Jeff Bezos&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:6">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://hbr.org/1996/07/increasing-returns-and-the-new-world-of-business">Increasing Returns and the New World of Business&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:7">
&lt;p>Wikipedia page for the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raymond_Damadian">Inventor of MRI scanner&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:8">
&lt;p>Here is a YouTube link to the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?app=desktop&amp;amp;v=GdlO8MwLGy0&amp;amp;t=139s">David Elliot Shaw Interview&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:8" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description><author>hi@asindu.xyz (Asindu Drileba)</author><guid>https://asindu.xyz/posts/the-nature-of-technology-book-review/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Random walk in 2 lines of J</title><link>https://asindu.xyz/posts/random-walk-in-2-lines-of-j/</link><description>&lt;p>Of all the many programming languages, none has quite caught my attention like the &amp;ldquo;Iversonian&amp;rdquo;
programming languages, that is, languages like &lt;a href="https://tryapl.org/">APL&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://estradajke.github.io/k9-simples/k9/index.html">Shakti&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://pkg.go.dev/robpike.io/ivy">Ivy&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://mlochbaum.github.io/BQN/">BQN&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="http://www.jsoftware.com/">J&lt;/a> - the subject of this blog post.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One misconception is that languages like J are in the same caliber as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brainfuck">Brain F**k&lt;/a> and other &lt;a href="https://esolangs.org/wiki/Main_Page">esoteric&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://github.com/topics/golfing-language">golfing&lt;/a> languages which are mostly for recreational programming.
Languages like J however were designed to be a replacement to traditional maths notation - an interface for thinking or a &lt;a href="https://www.jsoftware.com/papers/tot.htm">tool of thought&lt;/a> as their inventor &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenneth_E._Iverson">Kenneth E. Iverson&lt;/a> called them in his Turing Award lecture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this blog post I am going to introduce the J programming language by using it as a &amp;ldquo;tool of thought&amp;rdquo; to explain the 1 dimensional random walk.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>To try out the code yourself you will have to install the J interpreter. The easiest way to get it working on Mac is through running the &lt;a href="https://formulae.brew.sh/cask/j">brew formula&lt;/a> &lt;code>brew install --cask j&lt;/code>. For other platforms,
see the &lt;a href="https://code.jsoftware.com/wiki/System/Installation/J903/Zips">installation instructions&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="first-a-random-walk-in-5-lines">First, a random walk in 5 lines. &lt;a href="#first-a-random-walk-in-5-lines" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The 1 dimensional random walk is a toy model used in finance for creating what may look like stock market prices.
In it&amp;rsquo;s simplest form, a 1 dimensional random walk consists of;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Several steps (a list of values), and at each step (for each value) it is either up (indicated by &lt;code>+1&lt;/code>) or down (indicated by &lt;code>-1&lt;/code>).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Note that the value of each step &lt;code>-1&lt;/code> or &lt;code>+1&lt;/code> is chosen at random. Hence the term &amp;lsquo;random walk&amp;rsquo;. So a random walk is basically a list of &lt;code>-1&lt;/code> and &lt;code>+1&lt;/code> generated at random.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To attain the &amp;lsquo;synthetic price&amp;rsquo; or what looks like stock prices, we simply compute the running sum of this list of random &lt;code>-1&lt;/code> and &lt;code>+1&lt;/code> integers.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The entire toy model of prices we described above is created using the J code below. Let me describe how.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-j">load 'plot' NB. Import the utility for plotting charts
indices =: ? 100#2 NB. Generate indices
walks =: indices { _1 1 NB. Use indices to create list of -1 &amp;amp; +1 integers
running_sum =: +/\ walks NB. Compute synthetic price
plot running_sum NB. Plot the running sum
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;h3 id="generating-indices">Generating indices. &lt;a href="#generating-indices" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>An index refers to the position of an item in a list. For example, the list &lt;code>1 2 3 4&lt;/code> has the indices &lt;code>0&lt;/code> for &lt;code>1&lt;/code>, &lt;code>2&lt;/code>, &lt;code>3&lt;/code>, with the index &lt;code>0&lt;/code> referring to &lt;code>1&lt;/code>, the index &lt;code>1&lt;/code> referring to &lt;code>2&lt;/code>, the index &lt;code>2&lt;/code> referring to &lt;code>3&lt;/code> and the index &lt;code>3&lt;/code> referring to &lt;code>4&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Line 2, &lt;code>indices =: ? 100#2&lt;/code> generates indices as follows.
The &lt;code>#&lt;/code> symbol takes in two values &lt;code>2&lt;/code> and &lt;code>100&lt;/code> and what it does is that it &amp;ldquo;copies&amp;rdquo; &lt;code>2&lt;/code> into an list &lt;code>100&lt;/code> times. For example &lt;code>5#1&lt;/code> copies &lt;code>1&lt;/code> five times to give &lt;code>1 1 1 1 1&lt;/code>. So &lt;code>100#2&lt;/code> returns &lt;code>2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 ... 2&lt;/code> up to the 100&amp;rsquo;th &lt;code>2&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;code>?&lt;/code> symbol generates random numbers, you can think of it as rolling a dice. For example, &lt;code>? 5&lt;/code> may randomly return &lt;code>0&lt;/code>, &lt;code>1&lt;/code>, &lt;code>2&lt;/code>, &lt;code>3&lt;/code> or &lt;code>4&lt;/code>. So &lt;code>? 5&lt;/code> can be read as &amp;ldquo;generate a random number below 5&amp;rdquo;, &lt;code>0&lt;/code> is included since the values &lt;code>?&lt;/code> generates are always greater than or equal to &lt;code>0&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And finally to generate a list of random numbers, we simply give &lt;code>?&lt;/code> a list of numbers for example &lt;code>? 3 3 3 3 3&lt;/code> may generate &lt;code>1 1 0 2 2&lt;/code> i.e 5 random numbers under &lt;code>3&lt;/code>.
Recall that in line 2, &lt;code>100#2&lt;/code> generates a list of one hundred &lt;code>2&lt;/code>&amp;rsquo;s. &lt;code>?&lt;/code> then takes the list of one hundred &lt;code>2&lt;/code>&amp;rsquo;s and for each &lt;code>2&lt;/code> it generates a random number less than &lt;code>2&lt;/code> i.e &lt;code>0&lt;/code> or &lt;code>1&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>? 100#2&lt;/code> can be read as &amp;ldquo;generate a list one hundred 2&amp;rsquo;s and for each item in the list, generate a random integer less that 2&amp;rdquo;. This will return a random list of 100 items made up of exclusively 1&amp;rsquo;s and 0&amp;rsquo;s looking like &lt;code>0 0 1 1 0 0 1 1 1 0 0 1 0 1 0 1 1 0 1 0 1 1 0 1 ...&lt;/code>. We then store this in a variable called &lt;code>indices&lt;/code> using &lt;code>=:&lt;/code>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is what we shall use as our indices.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="use-indices-to-create-list-of--1--1-integers">Use indices to create list of -1 &amp;amp; +1 integers. &lt;a href="#use-indices-to-create-list-of--1--1-integers" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In line 3, we use our list of 0&amp;rsquo;s and 1&amp;rsquo;s as indices to generate a random walk (random list made up of -1&amp;rsquo;s &amp;amp; +1&amp;rsquo;s).
To do this, we use the symbol &lt;code>{&lt;/code> in &lt;code>indices { _1 1&lt;/code> that takes in two sets of values, first is the variable &lt;code>indices&lt;/code> which is a list of randomly generated 1&amp;rsquo;s &amp;amp; 0&amp;rsquo;s. On the other side of &lt;code>{&lt;/code> is &lt;code>_1 1&lt;/code>, which represent the directions of our random walk &lt;code>_1&lt;/code> for &lt;code>-1&lt;/code> (down) and &lt;code>1&lt;/code> for &lt;code>+1&lt;/code> or (up).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What &lt;code>{&lt;/code> does is that it &amp;ldquo;pulls&amp;rdquo; items from a list given an index.
The list &lt;code>_1 1&lt;/code> has the indices &lt;code>0&lt;/code> for &lt;code>_1&lt;/code> and &lt;code>1&lt;/code> for &lt;code>1&lt;/code>, recall that an index refers to the position of an item in the list. So the statement &lt;code>0 { _1 1&lt;/code> would return &lt;code>_1&lt;/code> and &lt;code>1 { _1 1&lt;/code> returns &lt;code>1&lt;/code> from the list.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A list of indices would also return a list of items, for instance &lt;code>1 0 0 1 { _1 1&lt;/code> would return &lt;code>1 _1 _1 1&lt;/code>. Which is similar to what &lt;code>indices { _1 1&lt;/code> is doing. Since &lt;code>indices&lt;/code> is a list of random one hundred 1&amp;rsquo;s and 0&amp;rsquo;s it will also randomly pull out a list of &lt;code>_1&lt;/code> and &lt;code>1&lt;/code> thus giving us a list like &lt;code>_1 _1 1 1 _1 _1 _1 _1 _1 _1 1 _1 ...&lt;/code> up to the one hundredth index. Which is the random walk of 100 steps.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We also store this list into a variable &lt;code>walks&lt;/code> using &lt;code>=:&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="compute-the-synthetic-prices">Compute the synthetic prices. &lt;a href="#compute-the-synthetic-prices" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In line 4 we use &lt;code>+/\&lt;/code> the running sum of the random walk. For example &lt;code>+/\ 1 1 1 1 1 1 1&lt;/code> computes the running sum of seven 1&amp;rsquo;s, which gives us &lt;code>1 2 3 4 5 6 7&lt;/code>. Which is exactly what we do with &lt;code>+/\ walks&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since &lt;code>walks&lt;/code> is made up of randomly generated &lt;code>_1&lt;/code> and &lt;code>1&lt;/code>, it&amp;rsquo;s running sum will equally fluctuate up and down. The running sum of &lt;code>1 _1 1 _1 _1 _1 1 1 1 _1 _1&lt;/code> will look like &lt;code>1 0 1 0 _1 _2 _1 0 1 0 _1&lt;/code>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The running sum (synthetic price) &lt;code>+/\ walks&lt;/code> is then stored inside the variable &lt;code>running_sum&lt;/code> with &lt;code>=:&lt;/code>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="a-random-walk-in-2-lines">A random walk in 2 lines. &lt;a href="#a-random-walk-in-2-lines" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This post was supposed how to create a random walk in 2 lines of J. So below is the exact code above refactored to run in two lines.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-j">load 'plot' NB. Import the plot library
plot +/\ (?100#2) { _1 1 NB. Plot synthetic price/ random walk
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;h3 id="adjusting-step-size">Adjusting step size &lt;a href="#adjusting-step-size" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;code>100&lt;/code> denotes the number of steps the random walk takes. The more the steps the closer to actual stock prices the plot will look like.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="random-walk-of-100-steps">Random Walk of 100 steps &lt;a href="#random-walk-of-100-steps" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://asindu.xyz/files/8-random-walk-in-2-lines-of-j/random-walks/100.png" alt="Random Walk of 100 steps" loading="lazy" />
&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="random-walk-of-200-steps">Random Walk of 200 steps &lt;a href="#random-walk-of-200-steps" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://asindu.xyz/files/8-random-walk-in-2-lines-of-j/random-walks/200.png" alt="Random Walk of 200 steps" loading="lazy" />
&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="random-walk-of-500-steps">Random Walk of 500 steps &lt;a href="#random-walk-of-500-steps" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://asindu.xyz/files/8-random-walk-in-2-lines-of-j/random-walks/500.png" alt="Random Walk of 500 steps" loading="lazy" />
&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="random-walk-of-1000-steps">Random Walk of 1,000 steps &lt;a href="#random-walk-of-1000-steps" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://asindu.xyz/files/8-random-walk-in-2-lines-of-j/random-walks/1000.png" alt="Random Walk of 1,000 steps" loading="lazy" />
&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="random-walk-of-10000-steps">Random Walk of 10,000 steps &lt;a href="#random-walk-of-10000-steps" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://asindu.xyz/files/8-random-walk-in-2-lines-of-j/random-walks/10000.png" alt="Random Walk of 10,000 steps" loading="lazy" />
&lt;/p></description><author>hi@asindu.xyz (Asindu Drileba)</author><guid>https://asindu.xyz/posts/random-walk-in-2-lines-of-j/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Wisdom of rationals</title><link>https://asindu.xyz/posts/the-wisdom-of-rationals/</link><description>&lt;p>For years now I have been fascinated by prediction markets. The source of excitement is the idea is that you can use financial markets to do &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inference">inference&lt;/a> — just like machine learning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A famous example of such prediction markets are the orange futures. The orange futures market is one that allows entities
to buy oranges in advance.
How it works, is that one can pay $1,000 to receive 1,000 oranges that will be delivered next year.
An interesting side effect of this orange futures market is how it &lt;a href="https://selectabstracts.wordpress.com/2011/11/16/can-orange-juice-help-forecast-the-weather/">accurately predicts temperatures in certain locations&lt;/a> more specifically, the temperature of the locations where the oranges are from.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But how is information on temperature reflected in the market meant for selling oranges? Well, what actually happens, is that the &lt;a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/orange-juice-futures-soar-as-weather-turns-cold-1416604154">orange futures prices rise towards cold weather&lt;/a> and drop towards warm weather.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This phenomenon can be easily explained by the fact that cold weather reduces orange yields thus causing prices to rise (reasoning from the perspective of supply &amp;amp; demand).
This explanation however doesn&amp;rsquo;t account for the fact that the market prices start reacting to temperature changes
&lt;em>before&lt;/em> they occur. It is as if the market knew what the temperature would be &lt;em>in the future&lt;/em>. Hence the name prediction markets.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="how-to-buy-information-from-the-future">How to buy information from the future &lt;a href="#how-to-buy-information-from-the-future" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In the example above, predicting temperatures was just a side effect of the orange futures market.
But how do we design a market to predict an explicit event? For example, say you want to know if it will
rain tomorrow.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Step 1: Declare an event that will reveal this information  —  Say you want a market that can predict the weather.
For the rain example we can declare the event &amp;ldquo;It will rain tomorrow&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Step 2: Define events outcome  —  Formalize the outcomes of the event. The event &amp;ldquo;It will rain tomorrow&amp;rdquo; has two out comes &lt;em>Yes&lt;/em> and &lt;em>No&lt;/em>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Step 3: Sell betting tickets  —  Sell tickets for the event outcomes &amp;ldquo;It will rain tomorrow&amp;rdquo;. Buyers of the tickets have two options
&lt;em>Yes&lt;/em> tickets and &lt;em>No&lt;/em> tickets at equal prices. Buyers are allowed to trade tickets with each other.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>If it &lt;em>does rain tomorrow&lt;/em>, those with &lt;strong>Yes&lt;/strong> tickets receive money 2 times the price of the tickets &amp;amp; those with &lt;strong>No&lt;/strong>
get nothing.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If it &lt;em>does not rain&lt;/em>, those with &lt;strong>Yes&lt;/strong> tickets get nothing &amp;amp; those with &lt;strong>No&lt;/strong> tickets get money 2 times the price
of the ticket.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Loosely following assumptions made by prediction market theory, the true information on the event outcome for &amp;ldquo;It will rain tomorrow&amp;rdquo; will be
reflected reflected in the prices at which buyers are trading the tickets. &lt;em>The ticket with the highest price is the event outcome that is most likely to occur&lt;/em>. If &lt;strong>Yes&lt;/strong> tickets are selling for &lt;em>$2&lt;/em> &amp;amp; &lt;strong>No&lt;/strong> tickets are selling for &lt;em>$1&lt;/em>. Then we would assume that it will probably rain tomorrow.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-assumptions-of-prediction-markets">The assumptions of prediction markets &lt;a href="#the-assumptions-of-prediction-markets" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Prediction markets operate upon 3 main assumptions. The first assumption is that markets are made up exclusively of 3 types agents.
A classification of these agents is as follows.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The pure gambler&lt;/strong>, this one doesn’t have the necessary meteorological information. He/She is simply betting at random.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The accurate information trader&lt;/strong>, these traders have information they think points to the fact that it will rain &amp;amp; they are right.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Inaccurate information traders&lt;/strong>, have information they think points to the fact that it will rain. &lt;em>But&lt;/em> they are wrong.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The second assumption, is that &lt;strong>The Information is predictable&lt;/strong>, this means that amongst all the market participants, at least agent is an &lt;strong>Accurate information trader&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The last assumption is that people in these market agents will perform a &lt;strong>Rational participation&lt;/strong>. Rational participation means that, speculators will always prefer to place bets on event outcomes which they think they will make money &amp;amp; they will decline from participating in bets where they think they will lose money. For instance, a rational person should not be a pure gambler because they have higher chances of making money by betting on information they know at least something about.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The accurate information trader on the other hand will flourish in this market as they will always have the edge in the market &amp;amp; thus make money off clueless gamblers &amp;amp; people signaling wrong information. Meanwhile, agents that always bet on wrong information will go bust or switch to markets where they do better. This is what makes prediction makers so resistant to market manipulation, &lt;em>it’s a system where agents signaling wrong information actively subsidizes people signaling correct information.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In theory, markets that repeat themselves should improve with every iteration (since most agents that signal wrong information are bust).
Provided all agents have access to finite amounts of money.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-to-break-a-prediction-market">How to break a prediction market &lt;a href="#how-to-break-a-prediction-market" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Prediction markets may be highly resistant to manipulation, but that does not mean they cannot break.
For a market to continue doing correct inference (accurate predictions), the sum of money held by the
class of &lt;strong>Accurate Information traders&lt;/strong> should always be greater than the sum of money collectively owned by the rest of the agents.
This is because all agents have finite amounts of money. And it will not be possible to offset noise incorporated into the market by
agents with bad information.
This may however improve in subsequent iterations of the market (agents signaling wrong information go bust) thus giving prediction markets a self healing like property.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is often mentioned that prediction markets are based on &amp;ldquo;The wisdom of the crowds&amp;rdquo; &amp;amp; that creates a false analogy where people this it works for the same reason democracy does, but they are actually based on the wisdom of the rationals, &lt;em>a system where people don’t talk about what they don’t know&lt;/em>.&lt;/p></description><author>hi@asindu.xyz (Asindu Drileba)</author><guid>https://asindu.xyz/posts/the-wisdom-of-rationals/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pandemic Bonds</title><link>https://asindu.xyz/posts/pandemics-bonds/</link><description>&lt;p>When Bill Gates was asked in a Vox interview &lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> on what he feared most, his reply was not climate change or nuclear war.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mr. Gates was most worried about pandemics, deadly diseases that spread quickly over large regions, he goes ahead to cite some of the biggest &amp;ldquo;death charts&amp;rdquo; of history.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These &amp;ldquo;death charts&amp;rdquo;, where several spikes in which a large numbers of people died in a very short period.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first &amp;ldquo;death chart&amp;rdquo; he mentions is World War I, the second one is World War II, the third spike or &amp;ldquo;death chart&amp;rdquo; was about two times bigger than World War I (50 million deaths), but it was not caused by a war, it was the spanish flu &lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. This isn&amp;rsquo;t even the worst case, pandemics like the the black plague killed over 200 million (60% of Europe&amp;rsquo;s population at the time) about 2 times a bigger death toll than any war we have ever had&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="pandemics--preparedness">Pandemics &amp;amp; Preparedness &lt;a href="#pandemics--preparedness" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Pandemics are real &amp;amp; unpredictable as we have seen with Ebola &lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, SARs &lt;sup id="fnref:5">&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">5&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, and at the time of this writing, the Corona virus&lt;sup id="fnref:6">&lt;a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">6&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The problem is that, we are often not prepared for these pandemics. For instance, during the Ebola pandemic in West Africa, 11,000 died simply because the responsible bureaucrats could not mobilize enough resources in time.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="pandemic-bonds-and-how-they-work">Pandemic Bonds and how they work &lt;a href="#pandemic-bonds-and-how-they-work" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There was an idea from the World Health Organization (WHO) to use create a kind of insurance market they call a Pandemic bond.&lt;sup id="fnref:7">&lt;a href="#fn:7" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">7&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How it would work is that,&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>First&lt;/strong>, a pool of money (equivalent to whats needed to finance an Ebola pandemic) would be put up by speculators.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Second&lt;/strong>, The WHO would then continuously pay the speculators a kind of insurance premium. But if a new Ebola out break occurred in a new country, the WHO would use the pool of money (put up by the speculators) to facilitate the mitigation of Ebola in that region. This is obviously an over simplification of the 300 plus page document that explains how these pandemic bonds actually work&lt;sup id="fnref:8">&lt;a href="#fn:8" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">8&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> but I hope you get the idea? Its basically health insurance for everyone subsidized by the WHO.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="trust-minimized--pandemic-bonds">Trust minimized pandemic bonds &lt;a href="#trust-minimized--pandemic-bonds" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The pandemic bonds have however become controversial&lt;sup id="fnref:9">&lt;a href="#fn:9" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">9&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> probably due to their poor mechanism design&lt;sup id="fnref:10">&lt;a href="#fn:10" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">10&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Despite this fact, I think mechanism designers can come up with better mechanisms resembling these &amp;ldquo;pandemic bonds&amp;rdquo; that actually work in a society.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The great thing about Smart-contracts like Solidity&lt;sup id="fnref:11">&lt;a href="#fn:11" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">11&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, Scilla&lt;sup id="fnref:12">&lt;a href="#fn:12" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">12&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> &amp;amp; Simplicity&lt;sup id="fnref:13">&lt;a href="#fn:13" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">13&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> is that, they allow us to design trust minimized financial instruments, thus incorporating a strain of these pandemic bonds into what is now popularly defined as DeFI or decentralized finance&lt;sup id="fnref:14">&lt;a href="#fn:14" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">14&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We can have several of these DeFi (Decentralized Finance) powered applications to mitigate several problems around disease.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>For instance, Animal husbandry businesses can pay these premiums to mitigate risks around animal disease pandemics like bird flu or mad cow disease.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Charities or Governments can pay these premiums to to secure resources for fighting pandemic out breaks like the recent Corona virus. The recent Corona virus for example is so new, there exists no cure&lt;sup id="fnref:15">&lt;a href="#fn:15" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">15&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. In such a case, the pool speculators put up would be used for research towards the creation of a vaccine.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="event-derivatives">Event Derivatives &lt;a href="#event-derivatives" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Another way of using DeFi to mitigate disease pandemics is by leveraging prediction markets like Augur&lt;sup id="fnref:16">&lt;a href="#fn:16" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">16&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> &amp;amp; Gnosis&lt;sup id="fnref:17">&lt;a href="#fn:17" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">17&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> to create an &amp;ldquo;event derivative&amp;rdquo; that may assist in the mitigation of a disease.
Event derivatives are markets that pay people for accurately predicting events in the future&lt;sup id="fnref:18">&lt;a href="#fn:18" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">18&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An example event derivative is a market we can call, &amp;ldquo;Will it rain on Thursday, next week?&amp;rdquo;. Before Thursday next week, people can bet &amp;ldquo;YES&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;NO&amp;rdquo; on if it will really rain on that day.
If it rains, people who bet &amp;ldquo;YES&amp;rdquo; win the bet &amp;amp; people who voted &amp;ldquo;NO&amp;rdquo; have their money transferred to people that bet &amp;ldquo;YES&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Coming back to disease pandemics, we can have a question like &amp;ldquo;Will there be a vaccine for Corona viral infections?&amp;rdquo;. In theory, this &amp;ldquo;event derivative&amp;rdquo; should incentivize the release of information that may lead to the creation of an Corona viral infection.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The market can also be subsidized by an entity through increasing the stakes to be won if incase the market outcome ins &amp;ldquo;YES&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>Here is the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9AEMKudv5p0">video&lt;/a> from VOX media.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>America&amp;rsquo;s centre for disease control says this is the &lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/flu/pandemic-resources/1918-pandemic-h1n1.html">worsted pandemic in recent history&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_Death">Black Death&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/vhf/ebola/index.html">Resources on Ebola by the CDC&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:5">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/sars/index.html">Resources on SARS by the CDC&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:6">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/index.html">Resources on the Corona Virus by the CDC&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:7">
&lt;p>A great article from the Economist is, &lt;a href="https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2017/07/27/pandemic-bonds-a-new-idea">Pandemic bonds, a new idea&lt;/a>. There is also one a &lt;a href="https://www.worldbank.org/en/news/press-release/2017/06/28/world-bank-launches-first-ever-pandemic-bonds-to-support-500-million-pandemic-emergency-financing-facility">press release from world bank&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:7" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:8">
&lt;p>Here is the full &lt;a href="http://pubdocs.worldbank.org/en/882831509568634367/PEF-Final-Prospectus-PEF.pdf">PDF of the Pandemic bond prospectus&lt;/a>. You can also find more related documentation &lt;a href="https://www.worldbank.org/en/topic/pandemics/brief/pandemic-emergency-financing-facility">here&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:8" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:9">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-08-14/ebola-bond-pays-investors-millions-while-congo-battles-outbreak">Investors Cash In on Ebola Bonds That Haven&amp;rsquo;t Paid Out&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:9" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:10">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-02415-9">Pandemic bonds: designed to fail in Ebola&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:10" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:11">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solidity">Solidity &lt;/a> is the most popular smart contracting language but has &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=14691212">several limitations&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:11" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:12">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://scilla-lang.org/">Scilla &lt;/a> is designed to overcome the short comings of solidity.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:12" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:13">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1711.03028">Simplicity &lt;/a> aims to improve smart-contracts on Bitcoin, it is however still under heavy development.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:13" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:14">
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.ft.com/content/16db565a-25a1-11ea-9305-4234e74b0ef3">‘DeFi’ movement promises high interest but high risk&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, is a great article from financial times to get familiarity with DeFi.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:14" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:15">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/health-51299735">Corona Virus: Scientists race to develop a vaccine&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:15" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:16">
&lt;p>You can checkout the &lt;a href="https://augur.casino">Augur&lt;/a> event derivatives or prediction markets.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:16" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:17">
&lt;p>Another market for making event derivatives is &lt;a href="https://gnosis.io/">Gnosis&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:17" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:18">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://www.marketswiki.com/wiki/Event_derivatives">A more comprehensive definition of event derivatives&lt;/a> can be found on the Markets Wiki&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:18" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description><author>hi@asindu.xyz (Asindu Drileba)</author><guid>https://asindu.xyz/posts/pandemics-bonds/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Proof of work on layer two</title><link>https://asindu.xyz/posts/proof-of-work-on-layer-two/</link><description>&lt;p>Ever since Ethereum launched, they have had proof of stake on their road map. The main decision often cited from this transition is the claim that Bitcoin’s proof of work is a “waste of electricity”.
Even the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uTxRF5ag27A">creator of C++ complained about it&lt;/a>. But now I am talking about why we may need proof of work on layer 2 yet everyone is trying to get rid of it from layer 1 (the networking layer at which &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/consensus-mechanism-cryptocurrency.asp">consensus&lt;/a> is made). Why?
First, before we think of substitutes to proof of work, we need to acknowledge the role of proof of work in a system like bitcoin.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Emin Gün Sirer has a nice &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/el33th4xor/status/1006931729679044608?lang=en">micro lecture&lt;/a> explaining what proof of work is.
The conclusion is that proof of work is a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sybil_attack">sybil resistance&lt;/a> mechanism. Infact, it was invented exactly for that &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hashcash">back in 1990’s&lt;/a> for Usenet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Basically, it’s makes creating a block expensive so as to limit how many blocks can be created with in a fixed time period.
So if we are to substitute proof of work, then it’s substitute needs to be capable of Sybil resistance or better.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sybil-attacks-beyond-layer-i">Sybil attacks beyond layer I &lt;a href="#sybil-attacks-beyond-layer-i" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Proof of Stake is capable of mitigating sybil&amp;rsquo;s on layer one however, the concerns of Sybil attacks a stretch beyond layer one. For instance, let’s say I have a layer 2 based messaging app. How do you stop infinite streams of messages from spammers?
You have several options ;&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>First you can use the &lt;a href="https://www.inc.com/sonya-mann/earn-com-21-co-cryptocurrency-email.html">earn.com&lt;/a> model where you require every sender to pay a fee to the recipient.
Great! but this doesn’t scale properly. Imagine a Reddit forum where you had to pay $2 every-time you want to post a comment. Even if you can afford it, many people will not &amp;amp; you will be the only one in your forum.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Another option is now to use proof of work. For instance, before you are allowed to send a message or post on forum, You have to do a small proof of work before you post. You can adjust the difficulty of the pow based on the rate at which someone is posting.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Proof of work can also be used to establish decentralized identity for reputation systems in a way similar to &lt;a href="https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Fidelity_bonds">fidelity bonds&lt;/a>.
They work (fidelity bonds) by someone provably destroying bitcoins, to establish identity. The idea is that destroying bitcoins is expensive, so it’s less likely that the identity is duplicate, as duplicate identities are be expensive to make. Proof of work can also be as expensive as provably burning bitcoins. So instead of destroying bitcoins we can just set a pow difficulty &amp;amp; give agents what ever reputation tokens they deserve as long as they solve a given proof of work puzzle.&lt;/p></description><author>hi@asindu.xyz (Asindu Drileba)</author><guid>https://asindu.xyz/posts/proof-of-work-on-layer-two/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why bockchains are not mainstream</title><link>https://asindu.xyz/posts/why-bockchains-are-not-mainstream/</link><description>&lt;h2 id="the-current-state">The current state &lt;a href="#the-current-state" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There is a lot of hype about what the global distributed ledger aka &amp;ldquo;Blockchain&amp;rdquo; can do for society.
A &amp;ldquo;trust machine&amp;rdquo; as some people call it, that will bring the power of finance, data sovereignty and inclusion to the people,
hence rendering centralized intermediaries like Visa, Barclays &amp;amp; Facebook obsolete.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We shall achieve this by using a combination of robust, battle tested cryptography &amp;amp; game theory.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While this vision is plausible, realising it is not a easy as it may seem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The blockchain is not yet ready.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-core-barriers-to-main-stream-adoption">The core barriers to main stream adoption &lt;a href="#the-core-barriers-to-main-stream-adoption" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The blockchain, while being a new concept in decentralized distributed databases has also presented a very unique set of problems in computer science &amp;amp; economics that have never been solved at the time of this writing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Is this post, I will talk about the the 6 most important issues only with which if solved, shall we (blockchain enthusiasts) ever achieve our vision.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="1-scalability-issues">1. Scalability Issues &lt;a href="#1-scalability-issues" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The current bandwidth, i.e the data that can be transmitted through a blockchain with in a given time is simply too bounded for main stream adoption.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ethereum for instance does a maximum of 13 transactions per second. Visa on the other hand can do 24,000 Transaction per second and peak over 40,000 transactions per second.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So as you can see, the blockchain is thousands of magnitudes unable to manage a global traffic of financial transactions.
This is what they call the &amp;ldquo;Scalability Problem&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Coming up with a solution to scalability the problems without tarnishing the original value propositions of a blockchain (immutability/security, decentralization &amp;amp; censorship resistance) is not trivial. It has been nick named the &lt;a href="https://github.com/ethereum/wiki/wiki/Sharding-FAQ#this-sounds-like-theres-some-kind-of-scalability-trilemma-at-play-what-is-this-trilemma-and-can-we-break-through-it">&amp;ldquo;scalability trilemma&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> by Vitalik Buterine (Ethereum&amp;rsquo;s co-author).&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="2-lack-of-intuitive-private-key-management">2. Lack of Intuitive Private Key Management &lt;a href="#2-lack-of-intuitive-private-key-management" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Ordinary users will simply never wrap their heads around private keys.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Private keys, which are a string of text used to sign transactions and make other proofs(cryptographic).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The purpose for these proofs or signatures is for other entities on a blockchain network to verify identities &amp;amp; messages amongst themselves without reasonable doubt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Private keys have two main problems first, how to store them securely.
Anyone who can memorize, take a picture, or copy your private key can literally steal all your money.
Because they have your private key, they can make the cryptographic proofs/signatures and &lt;em>accurately prove to everyone on the network they are you&lt;/em> even without your consent. Even when they are not you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Second, you loose your key you loose access to all your money &amp;amp; &lt;em>no one can ever help you out&lt;/em>.
There is no &amp;ldquo;click here to remember your private key&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We need to first come up with something as intuitive using ATM/Debit cards.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imagine if your bank told you that, &amp;ldquo;if you forgot your Debit card PIN, you loose access to all your money with &lt;em>zero hope of recovering it how ever large a sum of money it would be&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the above was the case, I don&amp;rsquo;t think any one would use debit cards.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="3-contract-security">3. Contract security &lt;a href="#3-contract-security" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It is simply not reliable &amp;amp; safe for responsible institutions &amp;amp; individuals to deploy smart contracts on blockchains like Ethereum.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Due to the blockchain having an immutable and unpredictable state, Smart contracts deployed on such a platform are also expected to suffer from immutable bugs &amp;amp; unpredictable events.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a result, millions of dollars have been lost in events such as the &lt;a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/features/2017-the-ether-thief/">theft of $50 million from TheDAO&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.coindesk.com/startup-lost-160-million-still-wants-shake-ethereum/"> Parity&amp;rsquo;s $160 Million loss of funds&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was glad that Rick dudley &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/1AGHAuWz_4U?t=986">talked about this&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="4-consensus-algorithms-are-wack">4. Consensus algorithms are wack &lt;a href="#4-consensus-algorithms-are-wack" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The popular blockchains only don&amp;rsquo;t offer transaction finality i.e you will never be 100% sure that you have gotten funds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can only be &lt;a href="https://ethereum.stackexchange.com/questions/319/what-number-of-confirmations-is-considered-secure-in-ethereum">probabilistically to a high degree&lt;/a> (but with zero guarantee) that you have received your funds.
This is because in major consensus algorithm called Nakamoto Consensus, the miners elect the chain with the most computational work that are with in the same protocol i.e consensus rules.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For instance imagine your bank tells you that you that, &amp;ldquo;there is a 95% chance that we &lt;em>might&lt;/em> have your life savings, however you may also not poses it in 5 years in case we discovered that the chain with the most work does not have your transaction in it&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Yes, I don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone wants to keep their life savings in such a bank.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="5-privacy">5. Privacy &lt;a href="#5-privacy" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Just by knowing someone&amp;rsquo;s cryptocurrency address, you can know their account balance &amp;amp; transaction history simply by pasting it in a blockchain explorer like &lt;a href="https://blockchain.info">blockchain&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://etherscan.io">etherscan&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Meaning it&amp;rsquo;s very easy for anyone to keep track of your financial activities without permission.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You buy HIV drugs? I now know your HIV positive, Your paying schools fees? now your local kidnapper knows where your kids study.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Buying birth control pills? Now anyone in the world may accurately guess that your a woman.
No careful person wants that!&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="6-price-volatility">6. Price volatility &lt;a href="#6-price-volatility" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Very few people simply don&amp;rsquo;t have the stomach to hold a financial instrument that drops by over 50% with in &lt;a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2017/12/26/bitcoin-price-in-2018-could-hit-60000-but-another-crash-is-coming.html">a few months&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-can-we-do">What can we do? &lt;a href="#what-can-we-do" class="hash">#&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Most projects are building on platforms that have these problems regardless, in hopes that they will integrate solutions to the respective issues in the future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The risk they face however, is that the platform they built on, my become obsolete after a heavy investment of time &amp;amp; resources on the wrong platform.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Think how the &lt;a href="https://bitcoinmagazine.com/articles/bitcoin-now-useless-micropayments-solutions-are-coming1/">micro payments industry died in bitcoin because of high fees&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s like building your phone app around a windows smart-phone only to be made irrelevant because the next generation of mobile users will not be using windows smart-phones, but iOS and Android.&lt;/p></description><author>hi@asindu.xyz (Asindu Drileba)</author><guid>https://asindu.xyz/posts/why-bockchains-are-not-mainstream/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>